Register of the Ekaterina Ivanovna Murav'eva Papers, 1916-1948
Hoover Institution Archives
Ekaterina Ivanovna Murav'eva Papers,
1916-1948
49004
Murav'eva, Ekaterina Ivanovna, d. 1948
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoirs, and notes, relating to the Russian Revolution and political events in Russia and abroad. Correspondents include V. A. Maklakov, P. N. Miliukov, Ekaterina Kuskova, Vera Figner and other leading Russian political figures.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Refugees.; Revolutionaries--Russia.; Russians--France.; France.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.; Figner, Vera Nikolaevna, 1852-1942.; Kuskova, Ekaterina Dmitrievna, 1869-; Maklakov, V. A. (Vasilii Alekseevich), 1870-1957.; Miliukov, Pavel Nikolaevich, 1859-1943.
Biographical Note
Ekaterina Murav'eva was the wife of Nikolai Murav'ev, member of a group of progressive lawyers (including Vasilii Maklakov), active in the defense of radical political causes in pre-revolutionary Russia. After the February revolution he was appointed chairman of the committee investigating officials of the Imperial government. Between 1917 and 1922, both he and his wife were active in the Politicheskii Krasnyi Krest (Political Red Cross). In 1923, Ekaterina Murav'eva emigrated to Paris where she lived until her death in 1948. Nikolai Murav'ev remained in the Soviet Union.
Scope and Content
This collection consists mainly of Ekaterina Murav'eva's private correspondence. Of special interest is Ekaterina Murav'eva's correspondence with colleagues and friends from the pre-revolutionary period, both in the emigration and the Soviet Union, including politically prominent figures such as Vera Figner, Ekaterina Kuskova and Vasilii Maklakov and representatives of culture such as the artist Konstantin Somov. Also of interest is the extensive correspondence from Moscow, of her daughter Tatiana Volkova, a literary scholar and author of several works on Leo Tolstoy and his literary circle.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1916-1948 (Boxes 1-5)
  Personal correspondence of Ekaterina Murav'eva, including correspondence with her daughter and friends remaining in the Soviet Union and family friends and former colleagues of her husband, Nikolai Murav'ev, in the emigration.
  - General
    - Instruction of Ekaterina Murav'eva re her correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Undated (Folder 2)
    - 1920's (Folder 3)
    - 1930's (Folder 4)
    - 1940's (Folder 5)
  - Unidentified. Aleksandr(?) (from the Soviet Union) (Folder 6)
  - Aldanov, Mark, 1927-1936 (Folder 7)
  - Dan, Lydia, 1936-1939 (Folder 8)
  - Derviz, Mariia(?), 1926-1935 (from the Soviet Union) (Folder 9)
  - Derviz, V. D., 1916-1929 (from the Soviet Union) (Folder 10-11)
  - Dobrov, F. A., 1917-1925 (Folder 12)
  - Figner, Vera, 1926-1931 (from the Soviet Union) (Folder 13)
  - Fisher, Harold, 1929-1935 (Folder 14)
  - Golder, Frank, 1926-1929 (Folder 15)
  - Guchkov, Aleksandr, 1927-1937 (Folder 16-17)
  - Kerensky, Alexander, 1926-1932 (Folder 18)
  - Kuskova-Prokopovich, Ekaterina
    - 1926-1929 (Folder 19)
    - 1930-1931 (Folder 20)
    - 1932-1933 (Folder 21)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1936 (Folder 2)
    - 1937 (Folder 3)
    - 1938-1939 (Folder 4)
    - 1940-1948 (Folder 5)
  - Maklakov, Vasilii, 1925-1948 (Folder 6-11)
  - Marguliès, Manuel, 1930-1939 (Folder 12)
  - Mering, B., 1939-1947 (Folder 13)
  - Miliukov, Pavel, 1939 (Folder 14)
  - Murav'ev, Nikolai, n.d. (Folder 15)
  - Osorgin, Mikhail, 1926-1930 (Folder 16)
  - Osorgina, M., 1939-1948 (Folder 17)
  - Petrunkevich, I. and A., 1929-1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Smirnov, S., 1934-1939 (Folder 2)
  - Sokolov, N. D., 1916-1924 (from the Soviet Union) (Folder 3)
  - Somov, Konstantin
    - 1927-1930 (Folder 4)
    - 1931-1937 (Folder 5)
  - Ugriumova, Irina Nikolaevna, neé Murav'eva, 1925-1948
    - Undated (Folder 6-14)
    - Undated (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - 1926 (Folder 5)
    - 1927 (Folder 6)
    - 1928-1929 (Folder 7)
    - 1930 (Folder 8)
    - 1931-1936 (Folder 9)
    - 1939-1948 (Folder 10)
  - Volkova, Tatiana Nikolaevna, née Murav'eva (from the Soviet Union). Also includes correspondence of her husband Gavriil Volkov
    - Undated and miscellany (Folder 11)
    - 1926 (Folder 12)
    - 1927 (Folder 13)
    - 1928 (Folder 14)
    - 1929 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1930 (Folder 2)
    - 1931 (Folder 3)
    - 1932 (Folder 4)
    - 1933 (Folder 5)
    - 1934 (Folder 6)
    - 1935 (Folder 7)
    - 1936 (Folder 8)
    - 1937 (Folder 9)
    - 1938-1940 (Folder 10)
    - 1945-1948 (Folder 11)
  - Wojciechovskij, B., 1932 (Folder 12)
  - Zaitsev, Boris, 1927-1928 (Folder 13)
  - Zenzinov, V., 1926-1939 (Folder 14)
- WRITINGS, 1939 (Box 5)
  Miscellaneous typescript and handwritten drafts of Ekaterina Murav'eva's reminiscences re the Russian Revolution.
  - "A la mémoire des victimes de la terreure rouge", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - "Dva pobega", n.d. (Folder 16)
  - Reminiscences about the Russian Revolution, 1939. Includes reply to Trotsky's Les Crimes de Stalin
    - Drafts (Folder 17)
    - Typescript (Folder 18)
  - Miscellany (Folder 19)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1936-1945 (Box 5)
  Includes obituary and newspaper clippings of writings of Aleksandr Guchkov, obituaries of Nikolai Murav'ev, and miscellany re the Russian emigration's relation to the Soviet Union during World War II.
  - Guchkov, Aleksandr. Newspaper clippings of his writings and obituaries, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Murav'ev, Nikolai, 1937
    - Obituaries (Folder 21)
    - Letters of condolence (Folder 22)
  - Russian emigration in Paris, 1941-1945. Miscellany re relation to Soviet government (Folder 23)